Nobody could watch more ticks in the
S&Ps than I have over the last 40 years.
So that should give me an edge, but it
doesn't. There's no advantage to open
interest.
>> Makes sense. Makes sense completely.
>> I think degrees are invaluable. I have
been scalping for 43 years.
>> So what what are you looking at when you
when you're scalping?
>> I mean, there's no question that AI is
going to be an extremely valuable tool
in helping traders
Thank you so much Tom for taking time
out to talk to us and uh you have been
an incredible influence to me especially
I I know I'm you know I'm here in India
but then I'm talking about a decade ago
when there was nothing on the internet
about probability based options trading
and I still remember I was looking for
something related to options way back
then. And what showed up was an
interview with uh where you were talking
to uh Sheldon Nathan, I think so. And
that was long back. I'm not sure if you
still remember that. And that was one of
the old uh Tasty videos. And that uh
that's when I was wondering who this
person is. And then, you know, it's been
a long time and I've been following
Tasty content. So, thank you so much for
that. So, with that, uh let's just jump
in. For those of you who don't know Tom,
uh Tom is a true trailblazer in uh
modern finance. He began his journey as
a floor trader on the SIBO floor
spending nearly two decades in the OEEX
pit. He's one of the original traders of
S&P 100 index options. And from what I
know, he is a pure contrarian at heart.
Late in the 1990s, he founded Think or
Swim, an online options brokerage
platform that reshaped retail trading.
It was later acquired by TD America
Trade for roughly $700 million. He
didn't stop there and uh you know Tom
went on to found Tasty Trade, now Tasty
Live, a platform built with a simple
belief that people are smart. They
deserve to be challenged with real math,
statistics, and probability and not dumb
down content. Tasty was the first
brokerage to offer options trading in
retirement or IRA accounts in the US or
so I understand and then uh the
conviction this conviction led Tasty to
become one of the world's largest
digital financial networks ultimately
getting uh ultimately selling to IG
group for 1.1 billion in 2021. Awesome.
uh his trading philosophy is grounded in
statistics that is law of large numbers
encouraging traders to trade small and
trade often. Even after decades of
success, Tom doesn't show any sign of
slowing down. Having recently stepped
away from Tasty Live, he's now building
a new venture called Lost Dog. Um you
know Tom, I must tell you this one. So
um I had many people in my circle who
moved from India to the US for education
or work and whenever they they they talk
about trading. I ask them to explore
Tasty and they've always come back to me
uh asking me how do you know about
Tasty? We we've been in the US and we
don't know about it and they've they've
they've loved the platform. So so
something great that you've built I must
say. Once again thank you Tom and you
know it's a great honor to have you with
us. Let's get started. I was wondering
you would wear your signature beret but
looks like you know after uh Think or
Swim and Tasty the beret is out. What's
the story?
>> The story is after 25 years of wearing
the beret um I decided to go natural um
as I as I begin my next venture into
building you know Lost Dog. So um uh
it's been a beautiful run. I've had a
great time.
>> Yes. Um I've loved every minute of it
but um you know every once in a while
you got to change things up.
>> Absolutely. Absolutely lovely. So u so
let me get started with you know I I I
was just looking up a bit and um I I
understand you have you studied
political science at Sunni Albany. So
what was it at that point of time? What
made you choose politics of all the
things?
>> I I'm I'm a boomer. So I was born um in
an era where in America, you know, it
was
a lot of a lot of there was a there was
a lot of political sensitivity in the
early '7s, late60s, early '7s. Um there
was the Vietnam War. There was a lot of
protests. um politics and and
political activity was um uh was pretty
important to us in you know in
especially in my youth and and to be
fair there really wasn't such a thing as
a business degree back then. Um there
was you could take economics but there
really wasn't such a thing called
finance or business or entrepreneurship
you know back in the 70s. So I I
gravitated towards what I thought would
be an interesting foundation, you know,
political science. Um when I got out of
school, there weren't a lot of jobs and
I got an interview on Wall Street and
they offered me a job, so I took it.
I've been here ever since.
>> Lovely. Yeah. U so at at that point of
time after you got into this first job,
what was your sense of markets? you were
new to markets obviously but what was
what what what was your initial sense of
stock markets what did you know about it
at that time when when you joined Drexel
>> um I didn't know I didn't know a hell of
a lot because you know as a kid growing
up um very middle class I I didn't
really you know I never owned any stocks
I never had you know I never was
participating in the markets that much
um but I gravitated towards it pretty
quickly because I I liked the action and
I liked the the the risk aspect to it. I
was always a risk taker. So, I liked the
risk part of it. Um, which is why I
ended up on the trading floors in
Chicago because once I found out that
existed, you know, I was I was in
Chicago like basically next day.
>> Lovely. So, so as you get to Chicago,
was options as a product new to uh you
or was it new to America as well at that
point of time? Was it an evolving
product?
>> It was an evolving product. Options
started kind of in the mid70s as an
offshoot from the board of trade, the
commodity exchange, but they were just
starting to take off. And the CVOE,
which was kind of a new exchange at the
time, um, you know, was the biggest
option exchange in America. And it was
really busy. It was really active. you
know, options were just there was no
real indexes, so they were all equity
options and options were just starting
to take off. And you know, I I had
quickly gravitated towards options. I
loved it from the loved them from the
first time I tried them. So I was I was
basically hooked right from the start.
>> But then was you today we have a lot of
it on the internet. We understand Greeks
how options work, volatility, whatever.
Uh but then did people understand all
these dynamics even then with with all
you know obviously there was limited
information out there but what how did
people understand this product and uh
was it very different from how we
understand it today?
>> Oh yeah it was completely different.
First of all at the time when options
were you know first when they first came
out and became you know even started to
become popular they were strictly used
as a leveraged you know speculative
leveraged instrument. Um there wasn't
much spreading. There wasn't much to
options other than people would buy them
as a kind of a cheap shot, you know, a
inexpensive an inexpensive leverage
play. That's it. And it took, you know,
a couple of decades before
um and it took a couple of decades and a
lot of really innovative software
starting in the early 2000s to change
kind of the culture of option trading.
>> But then who would take the other side?
Was it was it folks like you on on the
floor who would take the other side when
many were buying?
>> When I first when I first started it was
me, you know, it was people like me.
There was a few there was a few thousand
people like me and we would take the
other side of every trade. There were no
high frequency firms.
>> By 2000
>> um everything was a done starting
starting to get done. The other side of
every trade is you know pretty much a
prop firm or a high frequency firm. And
today you know it's 99% of every trade
is interacted with a high frequency
firm.
>> Okay. Yeah. Yeah. So uh so there was
another question which I had. So floor
traders like you or it could be others.
How how did you make sense of the
markets? Was it some kind of a
directional play where how was it
discretionary? Was it systematic? If I
have to use these words where would your
thinking fit in? I mean I'm talking
about the days when you were on the
floor.
>> Yeah. So I think the the popular
misconception is that floor traders have
any idea what's going on. The reality of
being a floor trader, a pit trader was
that um our job was to take the other
side of what anybody else wanted to do
because we would get a small amount of
edge of theoretical edge to do the other
side. So it had no it didn't matter what
we thought like whether we were bullish
or bearish or whatever. It made no
difference. We just every day came in to
work and took the other side of any kind
of a customer order. That's all we cared
about.
>> And was there some metric to how much
risk you would you would take with you
overnight and all of that? Was was there
some math to it? I mean, as an exchange
member, there there wasn't, but you had
to learn quickly how to manage your
risk, otherwise you wouldn't survive. I
mean, in in the world of of floor
trading, only about five or 6% of the
people survived, and everybody else went
out of business. So, you had to learn,
you know, I did it for 20 years, so you
had to learn pretty quickly how to
survive.
>> All right. And and what the people who
wouldn't survive, they don't learn it.
I'm I'm assuming that they don't learn.
They would just go out of business.
>> They they trade too big. They have an
opinion. Whatever it is, they don't just
don't learn it.
>> Okay. And and they would be out of
business obviously.
>> Out of business in a short period of
time. Yep. [laughter]
>> All right. Okay. So, uh so this is the
other thing which comes to my mind. I'm
shifting a bit about um u when I read
about you one of the things which I see
is you you always been about active
investing and um I'm not sure if I can
call you you were against passive but
then I I definitely you know the sense
that I get when I read about you is you
you were always for active. I I just
wanted to understand uh double click on
this a bit to understand what exactly do
you mean by active and uh you know why
is passive u not the best thing if at
all that if if that's your idea.
>> Well first of all I I don't have any I
I'm not opposed to making passive
investments by any stretch. I I don't
want to I I I don't want to I don't want
people to be confused by you know what I
preach and and what I talk about and
what I teach and all that kind of stuff.
I'm never opposed to any kind of passive
investment. The problem for me is and
the reason I think everybody should try
active investing is because passive
investing is essentially dead money and
it's brain dead activity. There's
nothing to it. You you buy something and
you hold it until you're right. I mean,
basically you're right, you're wrong,
whatever. You just it's there's nothing
wrong with it, but to me, you don't
learn anything from it. you don't gain
anything from it. All you're hoping for
is that over time positive drift kicks
in and you'll end up making some money
over time. I'm totally fine with that.
But to me, that's not strategic.
That doesn't add real value to all your
other skill sets. So, the reason I'm
such a proponent of active trading is
because I want people to have takeaways
from investing. I want you to learn how
to be um I want you to learn how the
numbers work. I want you to learn how to
make decisions. I want you to learn how
to speed up the way your brain reacts to
risk. And I feel like there's so many
really positive takeaways from active
trading that there's nothing wrong with
passive, but everybody should try
active.
>> I I I get that completely because the
number of decisions that we end up
making while being active, that has a
massive impact on uh of course we make
mistakes when we are active, but then
that's how we learn. instead. I mean, as
as you said, there's definitely an
option to be completely passive and not
do anything about it.
>> So, makes sense. I I I I see sense in
being active, especially when it comes
to learning uh how to make better
decisions.
>> Yeah. I mean one of the most important
you know one of the most important
things in life I don't care where you
live I don't care what you do because
you know the way markets work the way
capitalism works the way free markets
work is he or she who can make the
quickest decision
understanding the probabilistic outcome
of most decisions
is the most advantaged or the most
successful uccessful long term. Life is
about making quick decisions. Life is
about making decisions. Those who never
make decisions never learn how never
learn how important the speed is, never
learn how to process things quickly and
they kind of spend, you know, much of
their life stuck in the same rut.
>> How do you compare that with an idea of
thinking through things and then acting?
So, doesn't it go against that idea?
Um, you know, that's an interesting
that's an interesting um I what drives
me probably more crazy than anything
else is when somebody says I need to
think about it.
It is the um when when when somebody
whether it's one of my kids, whether
it's somebody in business, whatever it
is, whenever somebody says to me, I need
some time to think about this, I just
want to walk out of the room and say,
you know what, we can't do business
together. Because
taking time to think about something
just drives me out of my mind. You
already know what you're going to do.
Everybody already knows what they're
going to do. Nobody ever says, nobody
that's ever a a successful decision
maker says, "Let me think about it."
>> Got it. Got it. Makes sense. Is that how
you came up with the names for all the
firms that you started, be it Think or
Swim or Tasty or Lost Dog? Is that how
you know intuitively you you you come up
with these names?
I have a lot of fun coming up with fun
names to build very serious pieces of
technology. Um, Thinkorswim was a
groundbreaking piece of technology, but
it was a silly name that I made up when
I was walking, you know, in my house one
night. Tasty Trade was a name I made up
when we owned Thinkorswim. It's a name I
made up that I had to negotiate when I
left um Thinker Swim to keep because
because I bought it with the company
credit card at the time and I and I
wanted it. Um Lost Dog is a name that
I've been sitting on for years because
I've I it's got a little personal
meaning to me but whatever. And so I
don't actually care like the name of
companies doesn't mean much to me. It
just needs to be something that's fun
that I feel I can market. I feel that,
you know, I've always felt that that
>> we are we do a really good job at
organically marketing our products, our
technology,
>> and I think having a fun name has a lot
to do with that.
>> Absolutely. You sure do, Tom. Uh I I had
a thought when I I was thinking when
when you decided to move out of pit to
uh move out of trading to start a
brokerage. Was there any other business
idea that you had that you kind of you
know compared with should I start
thinkers swim or a brokerage or should I
maybe start a hedge fund? I don't know.
So was was there some different ideas
that you explored? There there were
there were a bunch of ideas that we
played with but um I I never wanted I I
had managed money a little bit in during
my trading career and I did not like it.
So there was never any intent to go out
and manage money. Um there was an idea
when we started Thinkorswim that we also
wanted to build a derivatives platform
that allowed for options on
non-traditional things. So basically
wanted to create like a swap market for
an option swap market for anything that
was non-traditional. We built a really
cool exchange essentially for options on
anything, but we couldn't get through
the regulatory hurdles that um you know,
we couldn't get through the the
regulators cuz they thought that if
you're creating an option, it's like a
security and because it's a security, it
needs to be regulated and therefore you
can't do this because it's not
exchange-based. So, we had to kind of
drop that idea and we just focused on
building a listed option exchange. But
we did have some ideas about you know
this is 25 years before there was a
decentralized world. So yeah.
>> Yes. Got it. Got it. And did you did you
try that or you you just explored it
with the regulator and you figured out
it's not going to work?
>> No, we we never tried it. We explored it
with the regulator. Um you know back
then like I said there was no such thing
as you know as a decentralized
product. You know there was no no such
thing as an overthec counter product.
Um, so we explored it. We built some
really cool technology, but we never
launched it.
>> Got it. Got it. Do you think it's
possible today?
>> Um, not in the US.
>> Okay.
>> I think there there are some there are
some sites out there that do it in, you
know, the digital asset world. Um,
>> that that's that's exactly what I meant.
>> Yeah. I mean, but it's hard because it's
never been something that's been allowed
in the US. And I'm, you know, since I'm
based in Chicago, um I, you know,
there's not much I can do. I'm not
moving to, you know, Bermuda or or um
Cyprus, you know, so it's hard. It's
hard for me.
>> Got it. Got it. Got it. So, uh so after
Think or Swim, um then we had Tasty. And
when you started Tasty, was it the
financial network first or was it the
brokerage first? Was it the financial
network first?
>> Um, okay. When when we sold Thinkorswim,
>> I and I loved Thinker Swim, but when we
sold Thinker Swim, it was just the it
was time, you know, it was just it was
we were we were ready to move on. And
I wanted to build something
that addressed what I felt was a
financial media in the US and I'm sure
it's like this all over the world, but
financial media in the US to me was um
was very disingenuous. What that means
is
financial media to me didn't make any
sense. I as a viewer, I really don't
care what somebody else's opinion is of
the market or a certain stock. Like I
know that they don't know anything. Like
I know that if somebody comes on and
says they love, you know, they they love
Nvidia here or they love IBM or
Microsoft, it doesn't mean anything.
They don't know anything. They don't
know if that stock like so I don't
really care what their opinion is. I was
hoping at some point financial media got
got somewhere where they were talking
about strategies and numbers and you
know and probabilistic analysis and
explaining you know hey here's here's
why this option is priced here. Here's
what the expected move is. Don't tell me
some stock's going to you think it's
going to go up $100 when the expected
move is six, you know. So financial
media was kind of driving me crazy.
CNBC, Bloomberg, all that stuff. It just
didn't make any sense to me. So, I
decided I wanted to build a network that
was fun, that was different, that was
digital. Remember, we built Tasty Trade
before there was such a thing as
streaming networks. We were the first
streaming network. There was, it didn't
exist. And so,
>> so we built
>> I'm sure even the bandwidths were pretty
low at that time. I don't know how
people watched your show, but the
bandwidth we we did not have the kind of
broadband networks we have today.
>> Um, you could watch it. It It was We
didn't It It worked fine. Um, yeah, it
worked. It just It You're right. We
didn't have the bandwidth we have today,
but it did work. And
what happened was as soon as we launched
it, you know, we we took a different
approach. No news, no guess, no
technical analysis, no fundamental
analysis, just quantitative stuff, just
math. And you know, basically hundreds
of thousands, if not millions of people
gravitated towards it because it was it
was something that a lot of people
wanted. It's what I thought, but I
didn't know for sure. And I learned very
quickly, hey, you know what? This is
really interesting. We have something
here. So for the next five years or six
years we did just the network and then
after after the sixth year we launched
the brokerage firm.
>> Lovely. And um when you did the network
how how many hours in a day would you be
live or how what was the format at that
time? [snorts]
>> I did with Tony I did three hours in the
morning and a half hour in the afternoon
for 15 years.
I so I did three and a half hours a day
minimum. I did podcasts on things like
that. Um I did three and a half hours a
day minimum plus nights plus nights we
would do lots of special things plus
weekends. So I mean it was kind of crazy
looking back at it, you know. I mean,
we we broadcast over a we've had well
over a billions, you know, billions of
views. It's insane.
>> It must have been a lot of work because,
you know, it's not easy to be on a live
show every day for five hours and then
you you said you did something over the
weekends as well. Must have been crazy.
>> Um, it was. But you know what? I've been
working my butt off for 40 years. I am a
workaholic. I don't really care. So, the
craziest thing is when I did my last
show like a couple weeks ago, I was
like, now what am I going to do? You
know, like I I didn't, you know, I'm
like, all right, I'm ready. You know, I
got to I got to, you know, I don't like
to have nothing on my plate.
>> Are are you at a point where you you're
not going to office? You're not working.
So, how are you how's your day today?
>> Oh, no, no, no, no, no. I'm I'm I've
started a new company. Um I didn't even
take a day off. I started a new company
the next day. And I mean, we've been
building it for a while, but I moved
over the next day. Took over as CEO. And
um and now we have a really cool, you
know, um AI slash uh streaming network
that we're launching a brand new
streaming network on November 10th.
That's two weeks from today. Um, we're
launching a new streaming network called
One Lucky Dog and it's launching on
November 10th and then we're also
launching our software uh end of
November, early December and it's it's
just a different business model. It's a
different business altogether. I'm
focusing in the US. I'm focusing on the
wealth gap and I'm focusing on worker
inequity. I feel like there is nobody
has really addressed worker fairness
in using
math and quantitative statistics. So
basically what I'm doing is building
these crazy option models to solve
worker inequity and it's going to be
very interesting to see you know what
kind of takeaways what kind of demand we
have for it. I don't know yet.
>> Okay. And and um talking about worker
inequity or you know compensation
inequities. So do you think the existing
market forces won't solve it and that's
that's the reason why we need a
solution? The traditional way to solve
worker inequity is either through social
safety nets, through um equal
opportunity, you know, um regulations,
through minimum wage, things like that.
Those address the problem, but they
don't solve the problem. The only way to
solve the problem, and this is not US
specific, this is global. The only way
in every country to solve the problem of
worker inequity is through education.
And the only way you can empower workers
is through education and letting them
know kind of what they're worth so they
have context around how to negotiate and
you know and and and and how to build
the confidence to go after what they're
worth. And and and that's where Lost Dog
comes in.
>> That's where it comes in. Exactly.
That's the technology we're building and
that is the network that we're building.
Now,
>> this is not something that's going to be
very easy
>> and it's probably going to be hard to,
you know, it's going to be hard for a
lot of people to figure out right first
what we're doing and how we're doing it.
But I am going to go after um CEOs that
make way too much money,
politicians that make way too much
money, and corporations that make way
too much money and don't treat their
workers fairly
and don't treat their employees fairly.
And I'm going to empower those
employees. And it's going to be one hell
of a battle starting in two weeks,
>> I'm sure. But you know this is when
you're going to put your political
science degree to work.
>> But we'll see about that.
>> Okay. So uh so coming back to financial
content, how do you uh you know you
you've been at the forefront of creating
online financial content even even when
nothing existed. How do you see it
evolving today now now that we have
YouTube and uh there's a whole lot of
content almost every fintech or you know
broking firm is trying to create content
to uh as as a means to engage with
users. How do you see the space
evolving?
>> Well, you're right and everybody's
trying to kind of copy what we built
over the last you know 15 years. The
challenge is most of these firms are not
that good at creating content and their
content is pretty much generic and it's
not interesting and they don't realize
that the reason that Tasty was so
successful is because we were different.
We created content that was a little bit
controversial, that was new, it was
innovative. It is hard to do that. And I
think they're going to find out, most
firms are going to find out the hard way
that it's not it's not easy to do. Um, I
do think that content can be a
differentiator if done right. I just
think that it's a challenge for most of
these old brokerage firms to do content
right because they're just not that
interesting.
So, that's the dilemma that they're
going to have to face. Um, I also think
that there's a credibility piece. You
know, one of the reasons that Tasty
worked was because I had a lot of
credibility as a trader. I mean, I've
been it's all I've ever done. And I
think that you can't put somebody up
there that's never traded before and
have them talk about trading and people
don't people just don't care. They're
like, "Okay, this is, you know, what do
I care what this person says?" So, I
think they have a lot of challenges. I
do think though that the true
differentiator in a world where
commissions are commoditized, in a world
where technology has been commoditized,
I think that you're talking about the
one thing that you can't commoditize
is truly creative content.
>> I makes sense. Makes sense. Completely.
So, in fact, I've been watching tra t
tasty content for more than a decade now
and I I don't think anyone has been able
to do that job yet. So u so I'm I'm sure
there is something in the DNA of Tasty
that you created that makes it so hard
for others to even copy it. Uh leave
alone make it better. But even copying
it seems to be a difficult task.
>> Sure. I I agree with you that that's you
know people always said to me you know
TD just launched a network trader just
launched a network. ID just launched a
network. And I'm like okay but they
don't have me.
>> You know that was my whole thing. I okay
great tell them to do whatever they want
to do I don't really care but they can't
they can't copy us
>> yeah so the other thought which I had on
my mind while we are talking about
content was today now what is your uh
perspective with with all this content
available on um on the internet be it
web or YouTube what exactly is the value
of university education now with if
someone has to go to um a university to
learn finance versus learning stuff by
themselves on on the internet and we
have AI as well to help now. So how do
you how do you see this whole space u
evolving?
>> Well, I don't think that you can ever
discount the value of a of a un of you
know university um degree and
undergraduate, graduate, PhD and
everything like that. I think degrees
are invaluable and for many reasons. Um,
first of all, there's a maturation
process that you need to go through.
Every every 18year-old, 19year-old needs
to learn how to grow up. They need to
learn how to mature. They need to learn
how to make friends. They need to learn
how to network. They need to learn how
to, you know, play off one another. I
can't stress how important
university um an education is at the
university level. It's not a it's of
course we anybody a 10-year-old can can
you know use chat GPT or um or Gemini or
whatever you want to it to to to find
out everything there is to know like you
know on basically anything nowadays but
that does not make it actionable that
does not make it practical and I feel
like although a lot of the curriculums
at different universities are outdated
or they have had a hard time staying
with the times. I I can't stress enough
how important the foundation is, you
know, um for PhD students that we hire,
for master's students that we hire and
for undergraduate and for people that
just have their um their bachelors um of
science or their bachelor of arts. They
are so much more valuable to us than
somebody that just is self-taught.
Um, it's not even close. Like, it's not
I I there's It drives me crazy when
people think, you know what, because of
all the information that's out there
today, this university degree doesn't
have the same kind of value. I would
argue it probably has more value because
on top of the university degree now you
can add on you know I think I feel like
what we do at Tasty is like a graduate
program in itself but you can add that
on to your undergrad while you're doing
it and next thing you know you have true
differentiators to establish yourself as
somebody that knows more than anybody
else and that's what I love about it.
So, so it means it's not just about
knowing stuff but it's also about
engaging with others and there's that
human element which um which being at a
university teaches is is is that what
you're highlighting?
>> Yeah, of course it's there's
>> beyond the education of course
>> it's the maturation process it's the
networking process 100%.
>> Got it. So um talking about um so one of
the things which um I had on my mind was
in I'm I'm I'm moving to trading right
now in terms of uh specifically talking
about markets volatility
>> what uh what exactly uh were some early
misconceptions that you had Tom about
the markets and which which you kind of
overcame over over time where which you
learned. What was it that you did not
understand in the beginning that you
know maybe over years or a few months
whenever that was uh it kind of okay
this is not how it works. So so what was
that?
>> Well it takes a long time to convince to
teach yourself a couple things
probably most importantly because we all
have you know big egos. We all have
ideas. It took me a really long time to
realize that I really don't know what's
going to happen next. Like I thought I
had some kind of an edge because all I
do is sit around and watch markets every
day for four and a half decades. And I'm
thinking to myself, nobody can nobody
could watch more ticks in the S&Ps than
I have over the last 40 years. So that
should give me an edge. But it doesn't.
And it took me a really long time to
appreciate that I don't have any edge
over anybody else in knowing what's
going to happen next.
I have a little bit of comfort knowing
that I've kind of seen everything once
or twice, but I don't have any edge.
if not edge Tom but over years
you would have developed an intuitive
sense of the markets as to u you know
what could happen next I'm not saying
you know you would know it for sure but
you would have a better intuitive sense
compared to others having watched the
markets
>> you would like to think so
I mean I'm a contrarian so I would like
to think so but markets Market can be,
as you know, markets can be incredibly
um difficult, irrational, what what we
perceive to be irrational. Um they can
be, you know, there's a lot of people
watching the exact same movie. It is
very difficult and there's only one
movie playing at a time.
It's it's it's difficult to be, you
know, to be different. It's it's
difficult to um uh I'm always ch Let's
put it this way. I'm always challenged.
It's never easy.
>> Interesting. So I I I I did think you
you would tell me that you figured out
something and some some holy grail kind
of stuff that but yeah it's it's
difficult. I I I agree that uh you know
but coming back to uh trading again you
you you've been a proponent of premium
selling but how do you deal with uh or
what's your thought on dealing with
uh what we call as tail events something
which happened in August 24 and then
April 25 again. So how do you what
what's your thought on dealing with
risk? I mean, those are tough
situations, you know, like any anytime
you're going to have outlier moves,
whether it's once a year, twice a year,
once every 3 years, whatever it is,
you're going to have some pretty wild
outlier moves. Um, I have learned to
deal with things by keeping my position
size in check. I don't think there's a
better way to do it. It's one of the
biggest takeaways of the last, you know,
15 years is learning to keep my position
size in check
>> and and go with it. It will happen, you
know, that it'll happen a few times a
year and just uh
>> yeah, I mean, I don't know that there's
I don't know that there's another way
you can get around um outlier risk other
than trade size.
>> Mhm. Got it. Got it. And um if you uh
when if you look at a trading strategy
or do you are you a systematic trader in
that sense? So that that's my first
question. Do you look at or do you
create trading strategies by looking at
data or do you recommend others do that?
What's your thought on that? um in terms
of designing trading strategies or
thinking about trading in terms of
systematic strategies,
>> I think that uh what I do is I apply
different strategies to different levels
of implied volatility.
Um, so it really depends for me. Um, I
mean obviously we want to be capital
efficient in everything that we do
because I do play kind of a game law of
large numbers, but on top of that I I
really base a lot of my strategy on
different levels of implied volatility.
If I think implied volatility is cheap,
I will do things that I think are um a
little bit better for low implied
volatility. And if I think volatility is
expensive, I will take on more risk
because I feel like there's more
opportunity.
>> And uh would you also uh test it or
simulate stuff? Uh that there are tools
available. I'm sure Tasty also has those
features where you can kind of back test
or simulate stuff. I mean, Tasty has all
those features for back testing. I
personally don't use them very often
because I've pretty much seen every
scenario. Um, and I can also, you know,
my mind works in
I I know it's going to sound weird, but
I see things in different levels of st
on different standard deviation levels.
So when I look at stuff um I built our
software so that essentially I can look
at everything from a you know with a two
standard deviation perspective and I
can't go outside of that because outside
of two standard deviations then it's
something that you know it's pretty hard
to quantify. So my whole world is inside
of two standard deviations and I'm able
to visualize that for really any trade I
make. So, so that's exactly what I
meant, Tom, when I said that. Have you
developed an intuitive sense? And I
guess you have. So, so in your mind, you
know what happens within two deviations?
Yeah, it it's pretty easy actually to do
in the US markets because most of the
brokerage firms require enough capital
to carry a two standard deviation move.
So, you can look at your buying power
reduction as one way of, you know,
getting to that number.
>> I get that. I get that. Makes sense.
Makes sense. And um are there talking
about in the in the in the world of
options, are there any other than
implied volatility, is there anything
else which you look at as a leading
indicator of what could happen for a
given uh spread or a structure? Do you
look at something else beyond implied
volatility? I mean, I occasionally will
look at um I do look at price because
not that I'm
I'm only making a subjective opinion on
price, but I do look for situations
where I think the price is at an
extreme. I also will look for extreme
situations and skew. Um I don't I don't
search by skew but I do look at the
option pricing skew to see you know how
much how much the market is pricing in
you know upside or downside pricing
skew.
>> Got it. Got it. And here in India one of
the things which a lot of traders look
at is um open interest across different
strikes. Um that's something which I
don't see much in in the US especially.
any any any idea as to whether it has
anyformational advantage over uh other
>> we we trade mostly liquid underlyings.
There's no advantage to open interest
especially if you're trading indexes or
um or liquid underlyings. I think the
only time we'll ever look at open
interest is if we're trading something
that's very illlquid just because we'd
like to know, you know, is anybody else
trading it? But I stick to mostly
>> 99% of my trades are very liquid
underlyings. So open interest is not a
factor.
>> Got it. Thanks. So um I I'll move on to
the next one which is you know Tom I'm
I'm a trend follower Tom and you you
you've been the little that I've read
about you or heard your in your
interviews uh I've not heard much about
trend following from you. So, uh, what's
your honest take on trend following? You
know, you can speak your mind. I won't
be I won't get offended. It's okay.
>> Well, so
>> I I'm a Curian, so I am not a trend
follower. If anything, I fade trends.
So, I have made my living fading trends.
That's how that's who I am. I don't
believe that there's such a thing as a
trend.
Um, I mean, obviously, you know, like
right now we're in a crazy bull market
and and you know, of course there are
stocks that go hyperbolic or they get
crushed, things like that. But I I'm not
somebody that believes that there's
anything more to it than it's just a
random case of multiple days in a row.
>> Dan, um, how do you make sense of all
these CTAs who run managed futures funds
and all of that? There's a whole
industry to it, billions of dollars to
it. So, how do you make sense of it?
>> Um, I don't try to I don't know exactly
what those guys do. I don't know how
successful they are. I haven't seen
results of a lot of um commodity trading
advisers who have been very successful.
I know that there's a handful that have
made money, but I think that's just
actually a statistical exactly what's
supposed to happen statistically. Um my
argument would be that in black and
white instruments like futures it is
very difficult to manage a you know a
directional fund based on trends. That's
just my
>> Got it. Got it. So so that brings me to
the question what does diversification
mean for you? Because if you are going
to be a contrarian and if you are
especially in the context of let's say
uh if you're in the business of premium
selling how do you diversify there in
that context if someone has to?
>> Well the the challenge there is you
diversify through um non-correlated
underlyings and through strategy. I'm
really good at using all the products
available to me. So for example, you
know, like I'll trade something that is
not correlated to the market like gold
or silver or, you know, bonds that are
not correlated to stocks. And so I think
that that's a big part of, you know, how
do we stay diversified?
>> Got it. So but it's but the
diversification is not in terms of
strategy, but more in terms of products
and assets is is is how is what you
>> That's correct.
Got it. Got it. So, um I I remember
there's another thing I'm not sure a few
years back, it could be five or six
years back or more, maybe a decade back,
uh Tom and uh you know uh you you did a
series on scalping with Tony. Okay. And
um I I I remember it was like some five
or six videos on scalping and it was
something very new and exciting to me at
that point of time. So I still remember
it that that's So one of the questions
I'm not sure if you would still
remember. So one of the questions which
I had was was it was sculping something
very intuitive to you or was there some
method to what you were doing? Uh I'm
just curious a lot of people uh asked me
that question. Um you know so I I
thought I should ask you.
>> Well I have been scalping for 43 years.
So
when you say is this something that's
intuitive to me or something that I
enjoy doing, the answer is yes. Because
even today, you know, I've been scalping
S&P futures this morning. I've been, you
know, scalping some some stocks um in
addition to my position trading. So, you
know, I mean, I've already made probably
30 scalps this morning. So, the answer
to your question is yes. I've been doing
it my entire life and I'll continue to
do it till the day I die, I'm sure. Um,
so yeah, it's important to me. It's an
engagement tool. It's fun. It keeps my
mind sharp. It keeps me on top of
everything that's going on in the
markets. Um, you know, it's it's
literally part of my being is, you know,
is intuitively scalping the markets. I
mean, sometime I think I'm good at it,
but, you know, again, I've been doing a
long time, but you know what? Um,
I do it more because I love it than, you
know, than anything else.
>> Okay. But you also say you're not a
chartist. So, what what are you looking
at when you when you're scalping?
>> Oh, I've never looked at a chart in, you
know, in four decades. Um, not I'm not
looking at anything on charts. I mean,
I'm just looking at price. I mean, I I I
memorize I mean, I know every single
price. I don't, you know, all I do is
watch markets. I don't need to look at a
chart to tell you, you know, where we
are or where we've been or anything like
that. You know, I I promise you, you
could not stump me on on where the
market is or anything like that.
>> Got it. Got it. Interesting.
Interesting. So, uh so yeah, so that
that's something which I had on my mind.
I'm so glad I you know I've been able to
ask you this question. Um there's
another question which comes to my mind
talking about strategies. So given that
you've been in the markets for four
decades, are there things that you saw
uh are there anomalies which you saw
existed at one point of time but today
you know it it makes no sense to trade
them and what are they if if if you if
you remember any of those?
>> I mean there's some indexes that um I
mean there's always going to be some
indexes and some stocks that used to be
super liquid and that just you know
they're just not they're not there
anymore, you know. um different indexes
that have dried up, different products
that have you know I mean there's always
some rotation. Um, so I think yeah, I
mean, you know, when I first started
trading, the most actively traded equity
was IBM. You know, now IBM's not even in
the top 100,
you know, so it just depends. When I
started trading, the S&P 100, the OEX
was the most actively traded index.
Today, it doesn't even trade anymore.
So, you know, it really just depends. A
lot of things change. I wouldn't read
too much into that because there's tons
there's tons of new stuff as well.
>> So as a as a trader if if someone is
starting right now do you think how do
they think about it? So uh how do they
kind of factor in um the the changing
possibility of products and so what what
kind of an edge should one develop if I
have to you know if I have to build a
career in this area if I have to become
a better trader? Well, I I think the key
to becoming a better trader is to is to
trade. You know, I know that sounds so
basic, but I think it's the kind of um
it's the kind of business where you just
>> you have to you have to get involved in
order to really understand, you know,
there's a lot of knowhow. There's a lot
of um experience that you get from just,
you know, pushing buttons and doing
certain things. And I it's hard and I
think you just need to experience it to
see if it's something that that you like
that gets you excited
>> and
it's there I mean I I know it's related
but then is is that how you think one
can develop an intuitive sense of what's
going to work and what'sn't or you know
are there things that you would see in a
in a winning strategy or something uh if
you look at a strategy you say Okay, how
do you develop that sense that hey, you
know, this this approach to markets is
not going to work. How do you uh
>> I I think it's really important that you
figure that out. I think different
people have different risk tolerances.
Like, for example, some people are very
comfortable with undefined risk. Other
people are very uncomfortable with
undefined risk. And I think it's
impossible to bucket everything, you
know, to blanket everything and and
generalize. I think you have to let
people experiment for themselves. Some
people like equities. Some people only
like indexes. Some people only like
define risk. Some people only like
credit spreads. Other people only like
naked strangles, you know, or naked
options. Some people only like to be
long options. Some people only like to
be short options, you know. Some people
only like to sell naked puts. It really
depends. I I'm not gonna I'm not going
to guess on this one. I just think you
need to play around and experiment.
>> All right. I think it makes sense. You
find out in each one of us would figure
out our own sweet spot over time.
>> I think that is the case truly.
>> Okay. So uh so other thought which you
you said you should punch in orders and
all that that goes uh so there's a lot
of talk about automation and using APIs
to punch orders all of that even even
here in India uh you know brokers are
giving out APIs which which can be used
to automate trades. What's your thought
on that? Is that the future? Is that how
a [snorts] lot of retail I'm I'm I'm
talking more about retail here. Is that
how retail is going to trade?
>> I doubt it. I I don't believe so. I
believe that it's very difficult to um
to code and to program um a trading bot
to do to think for you. Um I'm a brains
over bots guy. I don't see myself I
think that there's certain pieces of
technology that can help you in lots of
different ways. I mean, there's no
question, no question that AI is going
to be an extremely valuable tool in
helping traders. It's going to
accelerate the learning process. It's
going to help you look at your um
multiple layers of outlier risk. It's
going to help explain to you things
like, you know, um uh position risk and
trade risk and and it's going to help
you to quantify things that normally you
wouldn't even even thought about. So I
think AI is going to be a very positive
and valuable tool for traders. I think
trading bots on the other hand are going
to be pretty mixed. Um I don't see the
the I don't see them as being the
future. Let's put it that way. But how
about third party tools which would help
you let's say you don't no code
solutions as they call it. So you you
kind of configure something and it'll
execute trades for you rather than you
doing it for yourself. Um,
I find it incredibly hard. So, the way
I'll say it is that most of the high
frequency and prop firms that automate
trading
um, find it
almost impossible
to automate opening trades like that.
Almost impossible.
and their their technology is and their
data feed their data feeds are faster,
their technologies faster, and their
technology is much much better than
retail technology as far as execution
goes. If it doesn't work for them, I
don't know how it could possibly work
for a retail investor.
>> So, you mean a lot of trading is will
for for for the foreseeable future is
going to be manual. Is that I mean is
there a number to it? I'm I'm sure you
would know as uh in tasty the number of
users or subscribers um you know or
customers who use um the API to kind of
punch in their orders. Do you see a
trend there?
>> Um I mean it's a growing number of users
we but it's a very small percentage of
the order flow. So when you're talking
about percentage of order flow it's less
than 2% of all the order flow.
There's definitely a growing number of
users who are experimenting but again
the order flow percentage is really
small.
>> Got it. Got it. I'm quite bullish the
way I see it here. uh but it depends as
I said the in I think the story is
similar in India as well where the
number of as a percentage of the order
flow it'll be very small but then if you
if you look at it among traders a lot of
them are excited about using technology
>> I I I understand the excitement piece to
it I get it but I just think that most
people don't realize what you're up
against so if you are doing something on
your own you can make a lot of
subjective decisions, which is good. If
you're trying to run a bot, your bot is
going up against
the best bots in the world. You're
you're And now you're going to say,
"Well, so are you if you're putting in
your own orders." And the answer is,
yeah, of course. But it's a little bit
different when you're trying to run your
bot to go up against, for example,
Citadel's bot or Jane Street's bot or
everybody else. Their their their bots
are better than your bot. That's my
point. Your bot is a leased, you know,
couple of dollars a month, couple
hundred dollars a month. You're leasing
a bot from some third-party developer
who cannot compete with a hundred
million dollar platform that runs in six
milliseconds or a billion dollar
platform that runs in six milliseconds
that with better markets and better
theoreticals than everything you have.
And so
my issue with it is you are totally
disadvantaged right out of the shoot.
>> Got it. So, so you you spoke about Jane
Street and I'm not sure if you uh
followed the story in India where um the
regulator in India went against Jane
Street because they they claimed that
Jane Street was manipulating the
markets. I'm not sure if you heard about
that.
>> I followed it.
>> Okay. So, what what do you have to say
about that? Uh just curious what what's
your thought. Was it market manipulation
or was it a bad uh index in terms of how
the index was structured? What what's
your thought?
>> So
again, we're going to get back to you
know um the the Indian regulators cuz I
I have spent a lot of time with Indian
regulators trying to accomplish certain
things. I was not able to accomplish.
The regulatory environment in India is a
little bit antiquated.
Um it's it's very protective. I'll leave
it there. And it hasn't evolved to where
it needs to be to build any very
efficient and growing you know
marketplace. The Indian markets are very
limited to a few products and
to a certain type of product. Um the
technology, the front-end technology has
gotten significantly better in India,
but the exchange technology and the
regulatory environment has not kept up
with the front-end technology. So in
India right now you can get a really
decent piece of front-end technology as
a consumer but the exchange technology
and what you're allowed to do and the
way the capital requirements work on
exchange level especially for
derivatives has not kept pace with the
front-end technology. This is a very
kind of almost a normal situation as
there's growth in the system.
I'm sure Jane Street
here. Jane Street is not
they're not alter boys. Okay. It's not
they're they're they're they're a very
competitive firm.
My experience with them is their
technology is really good. And my guess
is that they took advantage
of really bad exchange technology and
really bad exchange routing rules and
things like that. And my guess is that
they didn't do anything that would be
even remotely considered illegal in the
US. But in India they disrupted the
marketplace and it was like as we say
shooting fish in a barrel type thing.
Yeah. And and so I guess I guess the
bottom line for me is that I feel like
this is this is kind of a blessing what
happened was kind of a blessing for the
Indian markets markets because now they
are going to accelerate
um regulatory changes and exchange
changes to focus on real highfrequency
market making which is necessary in
India. um the high frequency firms in
India, you know, are not as good as Jane
Street yet. And now that those firms are
getting in there, there's going to be a
completely the marketplace is going to
completely change and you're going to
get better markets, fairer markets, more
products, more capital efficiency, and
better exchange technology. So the
bottom line of this whole James Street
thing is that it's going to benefit the
entire listed marketplace in India in a
big way. Um that's how change happens.
>> I I I really hope it does Tom. Um that
reminds me about another thing. I'm not
sure uh if you followed this one. Now in
India post 2020 we had uh like like it
happened in the US we had a boom in
terms of uh trading as such not just you
know in options as a segment but across
so the the number of accounts which uh
which got open all of that shot up that
is one side the other side of it was we
we had a whole lot of um you know
traders who came into the market postco
and exchanges came up with different
products and um there were multiple
indexes on which options were uh options
were launched and each product had a
expiry on a different day. So 5 days a
week we would have some zerod expiry. So
this is not exactly the zero DTE u uh
what you have but then this is a new uh
a different product expiring each day of
the week and obviously it you know there
were a lot of u traders who took to it
and somehow you know the volumes of
those options were too high. So I was
saying we we had this and then the
regulator came in because there were
there was a lot of speculation a lot of
volume u which was going into these
activities and there were reports of
people losing money which which happens
obviously. So so they kind of shut it
down. They they kind of sunset three or
four indexes and decided that there's
only going to be two indexes on which we
would have weekly options. The rest of
them would not have weekly expiration.
we'll have only monthly expiration on
the rest of the indexes. That's how they
solved it. But then I'm not sure um you
know if if that's the best way to deal
with it. Uh do you have any thoughts on
that?
>> Well, it's not the best way to deal with
it because I mean you know the last
thing you want is the regulators quote
trying to protect you.
>> Um that's you know they make things
worse not better. Um I'm all for you
know as many products as possible. I I
just think the challenge there's there's
my experience in India because I can't
trade the markets there. So I don't have
like hands-on experience with the
markets but from what I I have you know
given um a lecture at the Mumb Mumbai uh
stock exchange and
>> um also you know I've met with the the
head of the exchange and and a couple of
the regulators there before um
>> and my my gut instinct says that that
you know the the exchange is trying to
play you
What they're saying is they're trying to
protect the individuals, but the reality
is they're making it worse, not better.
And I I just don't think you can't if
you want to protect everybody and not
let them trade. If that's what you think
protection is, then that's fine. But
don't throw out like, you know, partial
products. It doesn't make any sense to
me.
>> I wish I wish there there are more
voices like you, Tom. Okay. So, so that
uh you know how did US take to zero DT
talking about zero because we're talking
about zerodt uh there were questions
about market stability and there could
be you know some kind of systematic or
systemic risk that could come in because
of zerod and uh how did that play out in
the US?
>> Well, I mean take a look at it. It
hasn't had any impact at all. The
market's at record highs and there has
been no systemic risk that I can tell
from zero GTE. So to this point it has
not been a problem.
>> All right. Well, but what what were
there voices which said that you know
this is not a good thing. You know zero
DD doesn't add any value to to the
market or the ecosystem.
>> Well that's
you know I I understand that but that
assumes that you believe that the only
value to the ecosystem is that you know
is what people can take out of that one
specific trade. You know, my argument to
that would be that the value to the
ecosystem is that it's brought um a
record amount of volume to the um listed
exchanges in the US which is you know is
which is why we're the center of
liquidity for the entire world. So I
would argue that the exact opposite in
that zerod and other trading instruments
like that have kept the US as the true
um largest pool of liquidity anywhere in
the world 10 times over which helps to
fuel all the innovation and things like
that. So I I think it's it's very
shortsighted to think that okay you know
the product doesn't bring any um doesn't
doesn't serve any purpose. I completely
disagree.
>> Got it. Okay. So, uh uh you know, that
brings us to the end, uh Tom, and I have
a few questions. Now, you know, you you
were telling me in your initial days,
you would shoot, uh 5 days a week or all
of that and you continue to do that. Is
there a specific routine that you follow
to keep you going? U you know, how do
you do that? That that's that's the
question.
>> I don't have any hobbies.
[laughter]
But then but is there a schedule that
you follow in in in in terms of you know
to make sure that you are right there uh
just to keep you mentally uh going every
day and that's not easy I'm sure
>> um you know it's it's I think that's
personal in the sense that it has never
been it has never been a problem for me
to motivate myself and to get myself you
know to want to work. So no that's not
an issue for me. I I enjoy working. It
keeps me alive. It keeps me, you know,
young. It keeps me vibrant. I I It's
important to me.
>> I wish we all could have something like
that. So, u So, I I wish more more of
that for you. So, so what what comes to
my mind is I I'm I'm really happy that
you took time out to talk to us and uh I
really wish you you continue with the
same energy uh as you go on to build
Lost Dog. uh and uh I would I I we would
love to host you here in India whenever
you are here next. I know uh I'm not
sure if you uh you like this market but
then uh you know we happy to have you
here and uh I would I would love to
connect with you if I'm in Chicago. I
would love to I would love to take you
out for an an amazing dinner in Chicago
and if I get to India I will um for sure
let you know if if I get back and I I
assume I will at some point. I just
don't have it in my immediate plans.
>> Lovely. Thank you so much Tom. Thank you
for taking time out and uh you know I
hope to have you back again sometime on
the show.
>> Thanks. Thanks Andy. Appreciate it.
>> Thank you. Thank you Tom.